Today we dive into a truly incredible investigation conducted by economist Alberto
Alesina and Sottim.
It is an analysis that reveals a link that is nothing short of unexpected between family affection,
our most deep-rooted cultural values, and labor market laws.
In short, a completely new and decidedly fascinating perspective for understanding the
economic choices of nations.
Let's start immediately with a paradox, a real brain-teaser that has baffled economists
for decades.
It is a fact that rigidly regulated labor markets tend to generate
higher unemployment and on average lower incomes compared to flexible ones.
And we are with you so far.
But then, despite this obvious macroeconomic inefficiency, why do entire societies,
especially here in Europe, continue to vote with conviction to maintain these rigid
job protection laws?
It almost seems like an absurdity, don't you think?
Okay, let's get to the heart of the matter and compare these two opposite economic models.
On one hand, we have the flexible labor market, a system that rewards efficiency,
sure, but which requires very high geographical mobility.
In practice, you must always be ready to pack your bags to chase the best
opportunities, receiving higher incomes in return.
On the other hand, there is the rigid labor market.
This model boasts high minimum wages and very strong protections against layoffs,
allowing workers to stay exactly where they were born.
The collective price to pay, however, is higher structural unemployment
and lower overall salaries.
So the mystery remains: why on earth would anyone choose the option that ultimately pays less?
Well, the answer lies in an absolutely unexpected culprit:
the strength of family ties.
It is almost funny to think about, but the custom of adult children continuing to live under the same
roof as their parents literally shapes a nation's economic policy.
Data from the World Values Survey are clear: family attachment manages to predict,
with almost infallible precision, the type of labor market a given society
will end up adopting.
Let's see exactly how this chain reaction works step by step.
It all begins in Phase 1, within a culture that places immense value on being united as a family.
This leads directly to Phase 2: geographical immobility.
Moving away from loved ones has too high an emotional cost—a real wrench.
Consequently, when workers avoid moving, we enter Phase 3,
in which local businesses acquire disproportionate market power.
And finally, we reach Phase 4: to defend themselves and balance the overwhelming power of companies,
citizens go to the polls and loudly demand that the state intervene to regulate labor.
This phenomenon translates into a concept that economists call monopsony power.
It sounds like a very complicated word, but in reality, it's simple.
If in a monopoly there is only one seller, in a monopsony there is only one buyer.
In this scenario, a local company finds itself being the only true buyer of the time
and skills of workers who, in fact, have no intention of moving.
It's a sort of trap: knowing very well that an employee would never pack
their bags to avoid leaving their family,
the company can afford to impose very low wages,
with the certainty that that worker is going nowhere.
And this is where the real insight comes in.
Summarized in this quote from the researchers:
"To limit corporate rents and to avoid moving,
individuals with strong family ties rationally choose regulated labor markets."
Exactly, rationally.
Demanding guaranteed minimum wages or obstructing layoffs
is not at all a symptom of economic illiteracy.
On the contrary, it is a brilliant and absolutely conscious defense mechanism
to neutralize the blackmail of corporate monopsony,
while simultaneously managing to remain close to one's family.
Analyzing global data, the differences are staggering.
Take the nations of Mediterranean Europe,
deeply family-oriented cultures,
where leaving home late is practically the norm.
There, regulation levels are very high.
On the contrary, if we look at Anglo-Saxon or Nordic countries,
where independence and early departure from the family nest are central values,
we find drastically lower labor market rigidity indices.
Now, someone might object:
but how can we be sure it's really the fault of cultural values
and not perhaps geography or the government in office?
To overcome this methodological doubt, the researchers found a perfect
and unassailable control group: second-generation immigrants in the United States.
We are talking about people born and raised in America,
who move every single day in the exact same market,
subject to the same federal laws and the same institutions.
The only thing that distinguishes them is the cultural background inherited from their parents.
Well, translating these complex econometric formulas into everyday reality,
the results are breathtaking.
Even if immersed in the same, identical American market,
it is the culture of origin that dictates the law on economic destinies.
Immigrants from cultures with strong family ties tend not to move for work,
face significantly higher unemployment rates,
and end up having lower salaries compared to their fellow citizens
who come from cultures where family cohesion is experienced in a less binding way.
There is one number in particular that helps us visualize the scope of all this: 7%.
It is the exact percentage drop in geographical mobility among second-generation immigrants,
in the face of an increase of just one standard deviation in the strength of family ties from the country of origin.
In short, an invisible but very powerful attachment to one's roots literally and physically slows down
the search for the best job around the country.
And perhaps the craziest thing is that not only economic outcomes are passed down,
but the political demand for state intervention is inherited as well.
Surveys show that these children of immigrants maintain a far higher than average desire
to have a secure job.
They are in favor of state bailouts for declining industries
and have an unwavering faith that it should be the government that regulates wages.
At this point, the most classic of dilemmas arises spontaneously, a true philosophical question.
Is it state laws and institutions that, over time, shape the culture of a people,
or the deep culture of a society that gives shape to its institutions?
What emerges from these studies is the existence of a true continuous feedback loop,
a circle in which the education of children and the economic structure of the nation
influence each other endlessly.
So the crucial point is that societies end up coordinating on two parallel tracks,
two self-sustaining models, or to use a technical term, multiple equilibria.
With weak family ties, a very free market takes over, a laissez-faire approach,
where absolute independence is preached.
With strong ties, however, the market becomes structurally rigid and the
young are taught to rely on the family safety net—two completely different ways of living.
And to understand how powerful this force is, we have to take a long leap back into history.
This study demonstrates an absolutely staggering persistence over time.
We start from regional family structures, born no less than in the Middle Ages.
We pass through the values packed in the suitcases of emigrants bound for America before World War II
and arrive straight to the present day.
Surprisingly, values from distant eras are still able to accurately predict how much
labor rigidity we demand today.
Who would have ever thought that the family dynamics of the Middle Ages would dictate the labor rules of the twenty-first century?
Exactly so: the classifications of historian Emmanuel Todd show us that the old
nuclear and independent families left a preference for super-flexible markets as their legacy.
Conversely, the communal-style medieval family, typically authoritarian, where children,
wives, and grandchildren all continued to live under the patriarch's roof,
well, that is reflected today in a citizenry that demands ironclad protection from the state.
And there is a crazy statistic to confirm it: a huge 19%.
Today, people living in regions that centuries and centuries ago were dominated by those authoritarian and communal family dynamics
are 19% more likely to demand that the government intervene to protect jobs.
It's almost as if the ghost of the ancient patriarch were there, invisible, guiding the hand of the contemporary voter.
Summing up this whole incredible and impartial analysis,
labor laws are rooted in a very deep cultural ground.
When attachment to family generates geographical immobility,
companies automatically gain enormous monopsony power.
Consequently, requesting state intervention is not an illogical slip-up,
but a hyper-rational defense to protect the unity of affections.
In short, what is coldly dismissed as inefficiency in economics textbooks
is in reality often a very specific social compromise,
chosen entirely consciously.
Which leaves us with a final, very, very deep question,
that goes far beyond mere economic calculations.
Considering all this, does maximizing at all costs
absolute economic efficiency and flexibility
really worth the price of having a geographically fragmented family?
Deep down, every society continuously makes this silent choice:
optimize pure wealth or protect the closeness of bonds.
It is a giant invisible compromise
that every day shapes the world in which we all live and work.
What is the right path?
It is certainly a great food for thought.